<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks | MICHELE SCIPIONI</title>
    <link>/talk/</link>
      <atom:link href="/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2020 22:04:30 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/foto_bw.jpg</url>
      <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</title>
      <link>/talk/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Matlab </title>
      <link>/talk/intro-to-matlab-whyehow/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2020 22:04:30 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/intro-to-matlab-whyehow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;embed src=&#34;http://localhost:43859/data/teaching/2020_IntroMATLAB_why&amp;how.pdf&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;440&#34;&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Direct 4D PET reconstruction with discrete tissue types</title>
      <link>/talk/embc2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/embc2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../data/conferences/EMBC2019/poster.png&#34; alt=&#34;Kinetic Compressive Sensing - EIEEE Nuclear Science Symposium and Medical Imaging Conference - 2017 - poster&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dynamic positron emission tomography (dPET) is known for its ability to extract spatiotemporal information of a radio tracer in living tissue. In this paper, a novel direct reconstruction framework is presented, which include concurrent clustering as a potential aid in addressing high levels of noise typical of voxel-wise kinetic modeling. Core assumption is that the imaged volume is formed by a finite number of different functional regions, and that voxel-wise time courses are determined by the functional cluster they belong to. Probabilistic Graphical Modeling (PGM) theory is used to describe the problem, and to derive the inference strategy. The proposed iterative estimation scheme provides concurrent estimate of kinetic parameter maps, activity images, and segmented clusters. Simulation studies and exploratory application to real data are performed to validate the proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kinetic Compressive Sensing</title>
      <link>/talk/ieee-nss-mic-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/ieee-nss-mic-2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../data/conferences/IEEE-NSS-MIC-2017/poster.png&#34; alt=&#34;Kinetic Compressive Sensing - EIEEE Nuclear Science Symposium and Medical Imaging Conference - 2017 - poster&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parametric images provide insight into the spatial distribution of physiological parameters, but they are often extremely noisy, due to low SNR of tomographic data. Direct estimation from projections allows accurate noise modeling, improving the results of post-reconstruction fitting. We propose a method, which we name kinetic compressive sensing (KCS), based on a hierarchical Bayesian model and on a novel reconstruction algorithm, that encodes sparsity of kinetic parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model has three key components: the model of the acquisition system; the kinetic model; and a Markov Random Field with an L1-norm cost function, defined in kinetic parameters domain. Parametric maps are reconstructed by maximizing the joint probability, with an Iterated Conditional Modes approach, alternating the optimization of activity time series (OSL-MAP-EM), and kinetic parameters (MAP-LM): a parallel GPU implementation allows synchronized update of all the voxels, computing the gradient of the log joint posterior at each iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experiments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;100 noise realizations of a simulated dynamic geometric phantom were generated using a 2TC irreversible model. A bias/variance study confirmed how direct estimates can improve the quality of parametric maps over a post-reconstruction fitting, and showed how the novel sparsity prior can further reduce their variance, without affecting bias. Real FDG PET human brain data (Siemens mMR, 40min) images were also processed. Results enforced how the proposed KCS-regularized direct method can produce spatially coherent images and parametric maps, with lower spatial and better tissue contrast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combining sparse kinetic compressive sensing into a direct reconstruction framework can help generating high-quality images and parametric maps, both amenable for display and quantitatively more accurate than what a post-reconstruction fitting can achieve. A GPU-based open source implementation of the algorithm is provided.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kinetic compressive sensing: improving image reconstruction and parametric maps</title>
      <link>/talk/martinosopenhouse17/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/martinosopenhouse17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../data/conferences/MartinosOpenHouse2017/image_poster.png&#34; alt=&#34;Kinetic compressive sensing: improving image reconstruction and parametric maps - Athinoula A. Martinos Center Scientific Open House 2017 - poster&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parametric images provide insight into the spatial distribution of physiological parameters, but they are often extremely noisy, due to low SNR of tomographic data. Direct estimation from projections allows accurate noise modeling, improving the results of post-reconstruction fitting. We propose a method, which we name kinetic compressive sensing (KCS), based on a hierarchical Bayesian model and on a novel reconstruction algorithm, that encodes sparsity of kinetic parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model has three key components: the model of the acquisition system; the kinetic model; and a Markov Random Field with an L1-norm cost function, defined in kinetic parameters domain. Parametric maps are reconstructed by maximizing the joint probability, with an Iterated Conditional Modes approach, alternating the optimization of activity time series (OSL-MAP-EM), and kinetic parameters (MAP-LM): a parallel GPU implementation allows synchronized update of all the voxels, computing the gradient of the log joint posterior at each iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experiments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;100 noise realizations of a simulated dynamic geometric phantom were generated using a 2TC irreversible model. A bias/variance study confirmed how direct estimates can improve the quality of parametric maps over a post-reconstruction fitting, and showed how the novel sparsity prior can further reduce their variance, without affecting bias. Real FDG PET human brain data (Siemens mMR, 40min) images were also processed. Results enforced how the proposed KCS-regularized direct method can produce spatially coherent images and parametric maps, with lower spatial and better tissue contrast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combining sparse kinetic compressive sensing into a direct reconstruction framework can help generating high-quality images and parametric maps, both amenable for display and quantitatively more accurate than what a post-reconstruction fitting can achieve. A GPU-based open source implementation of the algorithm is provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keyword-&lt;/strong&gt; parametric images,PET,compartmental models,compressive sensing,hierarchical Bayesian model,sparsity,Markov Random Field,FDG,GPU&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Influence of Noise in Dynamic PET Direct Reconstruction</title>
      <link>/talk/medicon16/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/medicon16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the present work a study is carried out in order to assess the efficiency of the direct reconstruction algorithms on noisy dynamic PET data. The study is performed via Monte Carlo simulations of a uniform cylindrical phantom whose emission values change in time according to a kinetic law. After generating the relevant projection data and properly adding the effects of different noise sources on them, the direct reconstruction and parametric estimation algorithm is applied. The resulting kinetic parameters and reconstructed images are then quantitatively evaluated with appropriate indexes. The simulation is repeated considering different sources of noise and different values of them. The results obtained allow us to affirm that the direct reconstruction algorithm tested maintains a good efficiency also in presence of noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keywords&lt;/strong&gt;— dynamic positron emission tomography, direct reconstruction, kinetic analysis, compartmental model, noise&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pharmacokinetic analysis of dynamic PET data: comparison between direct parametric reconstruction and conventional indirect voxel-based estimation</title>
      <link>/talk/emim16/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/emim16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../data/conferences/EMIM16/poster.png&#34; alt=&#34;Pharmacokinetic analysis of dynamic PET data: comparison between direct parametric reconstruction and conventional indirect voxel-based estimation - European Molecular Imaging Meeting - 2016 - poster&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dynamic positron emission tomography (PET) studies allow to quantify tissue-specific biochemical properties. Conventional pharmacokinetic analysis requires the voxel-wise time activity curve fitting performed on a sequence of independently reconstructed PET images. Direct parametric reconstruction methods combine emission image reconstruction and kinetic modeling into a single formula, estimating parametric images directly from raw data. In the present work a comparison between the two pharmacokinetic analysis methods is performed on simulated and clinical brain 18F[FDG] PET data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monte Carlo simulation includes 2D dynamic raw data generation of a brain phantom (gray and white matter) based on realistic kinetic parameter’s values. Attenuation and random counts effect are included. The Feng’s model is used to generate the input function. 20 realizations are analyzed, each including 24 time samples ranged from 10s to 600s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2D 18F[FDG] PET data relevant to the brain of a patient (24 time frames) are acquired by GE PET/CT DRX scanner. The same ROI-based input function (covering the carotid) is used for both methods.
The conventional estimation consists of a full OSEM reconstruction and one step of voxel-wise non linear least square parametric fitting with a 2 compartments-3k kinetic model. The direct algorithm is based on optimization transfer framework and performs, at each iteration, an EM-like dynamic image update and a pixel-wise penalized likelihood kinetic fitting using the same model as in conventional kinetic analysis. On simulated data we assess the goodness of direct method with nRMSE, normalizing the error on direct estimate with the one relevant to conventional estimate. Linear regression is then performed for each of the kinetic constants on simulated and clinical data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;nRMSE values for K1, k2, k3 and Ki parameters are 0.7722±0.0024, 0.7847±0.0077, 1.0003±5.16e-05, 0.9960±1.3e-04, respectively. Regression analysis on simulated data (fig.1) gives following angular coefficients (and R value) for each k-parameter: 1.03(0.99), 0.94(0.94), 0.88(0.91), 1.03(0.99). The same test on clinical data (fig.2) gives: 0.88(0.87), 0.70(0.77), 0.72(0.80), 0.91(0.95).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;nRMSE analysis on simulated data shows a smaller error for directly estimated parameters. This could be due to a slight overestimation of k-values in conventional approach, particularly evident on clinical data, as it results from regression analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
